Finding Aid for the Farington Family Correspondence LSC.0668
UCLA Library Special Collections
Farington family correspondence
circa 1702-1858
UCLA Library Special Collections
Farington family
LSC.0668
3 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
This collection contains multigenerational correspondence and personal notes of the Farington family. Reverend William Farington (1704-1767) was the vicar of Leigh and rector of Warrington in Lancashire, England. His son, Joseph Farington, RA (1747-1821), was a landscape painter best known for two collections of engraved views of the English lakes. The collection consists of manuscript correspondence to and from the Reverend William Farington and his son Joseph Farington concerning Joseph's art studies with Richard Wilson and his work and life in London. The collection includes the personal notes of, and watercolors and a pen and ink caricature by, Joseph's younger brother and fellow artist George Farington. There are also letters to an older son, William, Jr., regarding his naval travels in the West Indies, as well as correspondence with other family members.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 1951.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID:9942330063606533
Biography
This collection contains multigenerational correspondence and personal notes of the Farington family. Reverend William Farington (c.1704-1767), the second son of William Farington of Worden and Shaw Hall, Leyland, was educated at Brasenose College, Oxford, where he matriculated on 11 February 1723. In 1733 he became vicar of Leigh, near Manchester, a post he held for thirty-four years, and in 1766 he became rector of Warrington (a living that belonged to his relatives, the Athertons) in Lancashire, England. A collection of his Sermons was posthumously published in 1769.
Rev. William Farington's second of seven sons with his wife Esther (née Gilbody), Joseph Farington, was born November 21, 1747 at Leigh, Lancashire. Joseph became a pupil of landscape artist Richard Wilson in London in 1763 at the age of sixteen; the year after, 1764, as well as in 1765 and 1766, he gained a premium at the Society of Artists for landscape drawing. In 1765 was elected a member of the Society. He enrolled as a student at the newly established Royal Academy of Arts' (1768) school soon after it was established, though he still exhibited his work at the Society of Artists and became one of its directors in 1772 and 1773. Later, he became associated much more closely with the increasingly influential Royal Academy and eventually became an extremely active and influential member; he was elected A.R.A. (Associate of the Royal Academy) in 1783, and R.A. in 1785. Joseph Farington married Susan Mary Hammond (1750-1800) on March 19, 1776; their marriage was childless. In December 1780 Farington settled in London at 35 Upper Charlotte Street, Fitzroy Square. He produced his Views of the Lakes etc. in Cumberland and Westmorland in 1789, the first of a series of topographical works, followed by Views of Cities and Towns in England and Wales in 1790, and completed the illustrations to the two volumes of An History of the River Thames in 1794 and 1796. Joseph Farington was sent to the Netherlands by William Windham, M.P. for Norwich in 1793 to prepare illustrations of the siege of Valenciennes. He later traveled to Paris in 1802, and both trips contributed to his appreciation for continental art. Joseph Farington, R.A. is best known for two collections of engraved views of the English lakes; published Views of cities and Towns in England and Wales (1790) and 76 plates in History of the River Thames (1794). He wrote A memoir of Sir Joshua Reynolds for the fifth edition of Reynolds's literary works (1819); died December 30, 1821.
Joseph Farington's younger brother, George Farington (1752-1788) was a history painter, who in 1773 was employed with his brother in recording the Walpole painting collection a Houghton Hall, Norfolk. George studied with Benjamin West, and became a student at the Royal Academy. He sailed for India in 1782, and died at Murishdabad in 1788. Many of Joseph's other brothers pursued naval careers. His older brother William and two of his younger brothers, Henry (1750-1827) and Richard Atherton (1755-1822) were all employed in the naval service of the East India Company. His fifth brother Edward (1758-1790) died of yellow fever early in a naval career and his sixth brother, Robert (1760-1841) pursued a career in the Church.
Sources:
The Diary of Joseph Farington ed. Kenneth Garlick and Angus MacIntyre. Vol. 1, Published for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art by Yale University Press, New Haven and London, 1978.
Evelyn Newsby, 'Farington, Joseph (1747-1821)', Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/9161, accessed 7 Feb 2008]
Scope and Content
Collection consists of multigenerational manuscript correspondence to and from several members of the Farington Family, spanning roughly 1702-1858. Important figures include, but are not limited to, the Reverend William Farington and his son Joseph Farington, R.A. William's letters to his son concern Joseph's art studies with Richard Wilson and his work and life in London. The collection also includes Joseph's brother George Farington's watercolors, a pen and ink caricature, and personal notes.
The correspondence to and from Joseph's brother William, Jr., regarding his naval travels in the West Indies, is one representative example of the correspondence in this collection regarding naval life. The correspondence in this collection includes letters addressed to naval men aboard several ships, including the HMS La Topaze, HMS Ruby, HMS Hibernia, HMS Plover, HMS Thunder, HMS Clio, and the Bombay Castle East Indiamen.
The collection includes Joseph Farington's letters to a nephew discussing a naval commission.
In addition to correspondence, the collection contains personal notes, largely in the form of transcriptions of religious and literary writing, including biblical verses, sermons, and the following authors/works: Jacob Duchè; "Lady Brook's Memoirs"; "Sherlock's Discourses"; "The Bishop of London Lecture"; James Thomson's "Summer"; Hannah More; Henry James Pye; John Milton; William Cowper and Frances Maria Cowper. The collection also includes administrative/legal materials, including the "Will of Thomas Armstriding" and a document related to the nomination of a schoolmaster for the grammar school at the Parish of Leigh.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection was originally housed in 14 separate loose folios. The connection between the materials brought together in each folio was not always evident; however original order has been maintained. Each series is organized by folio.
Family papers.; Landscape painters -- England -- Correspondence.; Farington, Joseph, 1747-1821--Correspondence.; Farington, William, 1704 or 1705-1767--Correspondence.; Farington family--Correspondence.; Farington, Joseph
- Folio 1
  - Binder boards, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Transcriptions of biblical verses from the Books of Job and Psalms, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Transcriptions of biblical verses from the Books of Proverbs Ecclesiastes, and Solomon, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Transcriptions from religious and other writings originally placed within Box 1, Folder 3, ca. 1800-1815 (one leaf has watermark of 1800; Southey's "Madoc" not published until 1805) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Transcriptions of biblical passages as well as passages from other religious writing and the following works:
    "From Wogan-on the Lessons for the 4th and 5th
    Sundays after Epiphany"
    "Orton's Letters 1 Vol"
    "From a discourse by Sir John Suckling-"An account of Religion by Reason"
    "Gilpin's Lectures on Catechism"
    Planta-Helo: Conf Vol 2
    "On the Sacrament", from Stonehouse's "Friendly advice to a patient",
    and Robert Southey's "Madoc".
  - Transcriptions from religious prose and verse, ca. November 2, 1793-December 5, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Transcriptions from religious prose and verse (including of a poem by John and Charles Wesley entitled "Abba Father!") and correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1802 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Heading on letters: "Hoddesdon" and "Clifton" and are addressed to Leut. William Farington, H.M.S. La Topaze Jamaica
  - Transcriptions of religious writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Subheadings:
    "By the Right Reverend Father in God. Thomas, Lord Bishop of Sadon and Man / Concerning Spiritual Communion"
    "St. Luke 23... Do this in Remembrance of me"
    "1 Thessalonians 5:18 / In every thing give Thanks; for this is the Will of God"
    "Hebrews 12: 1-2: Patience...that is set before us looking unto Jesus"
    "St. Matthew 26:41"
    "A Prayer Upon the Day of One's Birth"
    "Occasional Prayer"
    "An evening prayer".
  - Transcriptions from Jacob Duchè and "Lady Brook's Memoirs", ca. 1801-2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "Extracts from Duchiè [sic] IX Discourses" (i.e. "Discourses on various subjects, by Jacob Duchè" (1779)
    cf. ESTC # T116264; at end": "WF in September 1801!" and "Rules for Practice" copied from Lady Brook's Memoirs by William Farrington Rector of Warrington and Vicar of Leigh" at end: "Transcribed from Lady Brook's memoir's 1745. -by Wm Farrington. Rector of Warrington & Vicar of Leigh, -- copied from his by A Harington-1802.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Addressed to "My Dear William"
  - Transcriptions from "Sherlock's Discourses" and "The Bishop of London Lecture", undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Contains transcriptions
    "from Sherlock's Discourses" (1772)
    cf. William Sherlock, (1641?-1707)
    and "from the Bishop of London lecture"
  - Transcriptions of verse, prayers, correspondence, and personal notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Transcription of verses from James Thomson's "Summer" with heading, "Inscribed to the Memory of Miss B. of Kensington", 1775 May 05 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    These are lines 571 and forward of James Thomson's (1700-1748)"Summer"; cf. "The seasons, a poem" ESTC # N021182. On bottom half of page is "Sonnet", the first two lines of which are "Parental Fondess, with they pangs excuse / The soft affection of a voice unknown!" Signed "EB[G]: May 5th, 1775"
  - Transcription of verses from the Book of Isaiah as well as other religious writing, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Transcriptions include
    quotes from Isaiah 57:13-15
    "Wogan on the 4th Sunday after Epiphany, Morn[ingsong] Lesson" and "Evensong Lesson", cf. William Wogan,
    An essay on the proper lessons, appointed by the liturgy of the Church of England ..." ESTC T124235; from "Orton's Letters, Vol 1"
    from "From a discourse by Sir John Suckleing" and "An Account of Religion by Reason", cf. "The works of John Suckling" ESTC # T099811
    Henry Hunter's (1741-1802) "Sacred Biography" ESTC T098655
    Planta-Helo. Conf. Vol 2
    Sir James Stonehouse's (1716-1795) "Friendly advice to a patient: and spiritual directions for the uninstructed" ESTC # T086231
  - Transcriptions of writings by Hannah More, Henry James Pye, and John Milton, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    On one side of the paper is the transcription of an unattributed quote from Hannah More's "Sensibility": "Since trifles make the sum of human things / and half our miseries from trifles springs..." and on the other side is a quote labeled as "Pye's Afred" (i.e. Henry James Pye, Poet Laureate 1790-1813's "Alfred; An Epic Poem" (1801)) and below that, a quote from Milton's Lycidas, lines 168 and forward.
  - Personal notes, 1807 September - October (Box 1, Folder 15)
    On the first page is written,"On first viewing my Father's Picture"; signed "R.C. 28 Sept 1807.
    On the second page, a copy or draft of correspondence, "To Mr. and Mrs.-on their Wedding-day. / Dear Brother and Sister...Your affectionate Brother and sincere Wellwisher, R. C. London 1807".
    On the third and fourth pages, "On the meeting of Eight Brothers 18. October 1807, with the intention of forming an annual meeting"; signed "R. C. 16th Oct 07".
  - Transcription of verses by William Cowper and Frances Maria Cowper, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    First sheet of paper has heading "On receiving my Mother's picture" with continuous transcription of verse through page four. At bottom of pager for is written "Cowper" (i.e. William Cowper's poem "On Receipt of his Mother's Picture")
    Second sheet of paper has "Cowper" written on top right corner of first page with a transcription of verses from William Cowper's poem "Conversation".
    The third, quarto size, sheet of paper also contains transcriptions, including quotes from Frances Maria Cowper's "Worldly Anxiety".
    The fourth sheet of paper has "Cowper" written in the upper right hand corner with a transcription of verses from William Cowper's "Task", beginning with, "The Lord of all, himself through all diffused, / Sustains, and is the life of all that lives..."
  - Transcription of religious writing, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Appear to be notes from and about religious and doctrinal treatises, including one by Mr. Tibbs, DD, Gray's Inn.
  - Personal notes, 1802 or after (Box 1, Folder 18)
    The folio-size sheet of paper has the heading: "The following account of the last moments of [Mr. or Mrs?] Pitt, were related by Mrs. Tomlin's-Wife of the Bishop of Lincoln." and the smaller sheet of paper entitled "Life of the Happy Man" with writing below. Both items are undated.
  - Transcriptions from Bowdlor's Essays, Stonehouse, and Bowdler, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Transcriptions from:
    "On the advantage of Affliction" from "Bowdlor's Essays"
    "On Christian Perfection. from the same" and "On Resignation. from the same"
    "On time, not wasting it in needless amusements from Stonehouse's Spiritual Advice to the Uninstructed" cf. Sir James Stonhouse's (1716-1795) "Spiritual Directions for the Uninstructed" ESTC T054036
    "Poems and essays, by a lady lately deceased" cf.Miss Jane Bowdler (1743-1784).
  - Personal notes and drafts of correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    On the single sheet of paper, the signatures W. Farington and Hammonds are sloppily written at bottom of page. The gathering of four pages indicates that it is a "copy of letter Mr[s?] Hammons Downy Park".
  - Transcriptions from Augustus Charles Thompson, Hannah More, and other verse, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Transcription of verse entitled "Patience" by Augustus Charles Thompson from "Songs in the Night: Or, Hymns for the Sick and Suffering" (1845), at bottom of page initials "A.M.". This item is considerably later than the other materials in this binder.
    Transcription of an unattributed quote from Hannah More's Sensibility beginning with "Since trifles make the sum of human things" at bottom of page in a different, less formal hand is written "Given by Amal[?]".
    Transcription two poems, one beginning with "Ye who the sickly couch attend" and the other with "Oh! Power supreme to thee my thoughts I turn".
    At bottom of last page the initials "A.M" and, in a different hand, "Given by A.Mal[?] August 13th: 02.
  - Personal notes, transcriptions of verse and religious writing, 1802 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    One of the sheets is folded in half to produce 4 pages, and entitled, "Prayer answered by trials" and "Why art thou cast down"
    at bottom of page 3: "I send you two of my favorite Hymns-the first I feel is particularly applicable to my present situation" and signed Wm. Farington, March 12, 1802
  - Personal notes and religious writing, 1802 May 03 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    The first of the papers is dated: "May 3rd 1802" in ink and in pencil "Cowper"
- Folio 2
  - Binder boards, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Watercolors, pen and ink caricature, and personal notes of George Farington, 174-? (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Items consist of:
    a 13 × 19 cm watercolor on paper of a rural village or farm, with signature "G. Farington, July 10, 174[3?]" at bottom right of picture,
    and verse & signature on back of picture, "When this you see / Remember me/ Tho' many miles /We distant be. / G. Farington. July 10th 17[??]"
    a 16.5 × 15cm watercolor on paper of ruins with initials G.F. on bottom left margin of page
    a 14.6 × 17.8 cm watercolor on paper of maritime or river scene
    a 3.5 × 3.7 pen and ink caricature of figure smoking a pipe pasted onto a 6 × 6.9 cm cardboard backing,
    and a small sheet of paper folded in half to produce 4 pages, only the first of which is written on.: "I have a persuasion in my heart, that if God continues my life many years, many of these things will die. I shall be more cautious by them and more humbly seek that wisdom from God..."
  - Transcriptions of religious writing by William Farington, 1801-1802 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Transcriptions mostly from writings of a religious nature. At least one page is dated at bottom: "Topaze September 15th 1801", i.e. HMS Topaze.
  - Correspondence from "A.K." to William Farington and personal notes, 1801-1802 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    First item is a bifolium folded in half to produce four pages; on first page, verses from Cowper, beginning with: "God moves in a mysterious way..." and on last page: "The above verses were written by a Lady a few days before her death, & left in her husband's writing desk", with remnants of a red wax seal.
    Second item is a letter addressed to Lieutenant W. Farington, H.M.S. Topaze, Jamaica, with circular hole where seal once was,with header "Clifton Nov. 3d" and signed, "Affectionate friend, A.K." Header; letter begins"I wish exceedingly to unite to you my dear & highly valued friend, because I am sure your wounded mind needs consolation nearly as much as ours, & I am the only one from whom you can hear by this packet after the receipt of your melancholy letters-my brother is now providentially I trust at Hoddesdon..."
    Third item is a letter, addressed to Mr. Farington and signed "AK" with the header "Clifton Nov 30th",which begins, "I hardly know how to hope that you can be a survivor amidst the wasting pestilence by which you have been so long surrounded..."
    Fourth item is a letter with the header Clifton, Feb[ruary] 2nd" and signed "your friend, A.K", "I feel so uncommonly deprest [sic] in spirits today that I hardly know how to write a letter that will not affect yours..."
    Fifth item is a letter dated "June 15th, 1802" and signed "your friend AK" which begins: "Your sister seems to think that letters from this family..."
    Sixth item is a letter addressed to "Lieut. Farington, H.M.S. Carnatic Plymoth" with two stamps, one "Cross Post 25 June" and the other, "Plymouth 218".
    The seventh is a letter with the header "Clifton June 25th": "Your most welcome letter my dear friend was received by my brother last night..."
    The eighth item is a letter dated "Sept 6th 1802" addressed to "W. Farington Jr. Esq., Hoddesdon" with the postal stamps "Bristol Sept6 02" and "1802": "The return of this eventful day naturally..."
    The ninth and final item is a single piece of paper folded in half with name "Mr. Wm Farington on last page., and signed A.K. "I will not send the book without a line in my handwriting..."
  - Correspondence from "M. Church" to William Farington, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    First letter has header "Clifton June 28th 1802" is addressed to Lieut. Farington H.M.Ship Canartic Plymouth, signed "M.C.", and postmarked, "Bristol June 28", and begins, "Not doubting that a letter from your afflicted friend will be most acceptable".
    Second letter has header "Clifton, Monday, July 5th 1802", is addressed to Lieut. Farington H.M.Ship Canartic Plymouth, is signed "M.C.", and begins, "I scarce know what to do about writing to you my dear young friend..."
    Third letter has header "Clifton, Saturday July 31, 1802", is addressed to "W. Farington Jun[ior], Esq., Hoddesdon", and is signed "M.C.", and begins: "When you said 'you will allow me to write to you..."
    Fourth letter has header "Clifton Sep. [9th?] 1802", is addressed to "William Farrington Esqr. Pans Wood near Didsbury, Manchester" has postal stamp "Briston Sept 25" and begins, "I should be sorry to disappoint your expectations..."
  - Personal notes & transcription of verse entitled, " "Ode to the Memory of Wm Cowper", undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Folded sheet of paper entitled "Ode to the Memory of Wm Cowper, Esq....By the Rev.d. T. Eisborne, M.A." and signed page 4: "M.C." Smaller piece of paper contains lines, "I lend you this Book also, which treats upon the same subject as Leslie..."
  - Correspondence from M. Church to William Farington, 1802-3 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Dates and headings of letters are:
    Clifton, [Oct?] 16th 1802
    Clifton, [Oct?] 28th 1802
    Clifton, Dec. 5th 1802
    Clifton Thursday Dec. 9th
    Clifton Dec. 14th 1802
    Dec. [10 or 16], 1802.
    All letters are from "M.C" and addressed to William Farington at several addresses:
    Pans Woood, Didsbury, Manchester
    35 Upper Charlotte Street, Fitzroy Square, London
    Hoddesdon Herts.
    on board the Bombay Castle
    Indiaman, Downs.
    Interspersed with letters are transcriptions of religious writings, including those by M. Hale.
  - Correspondence from Maria Church to William Farington and personal notes, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    First letter (10 pages) is undated and is signed: "your very sincere friend, Maria Church"; it opens "Oh Farington! You have been called to [?] but painful, but sacred office-I have often wished it had been mine..." and discusses her husband's death.
    The second letter (4 pages) is dated "Feb. 2nd 1802" and signed "your sincere friend M.C." but also contains the note over the address "from Mr. Ward, Chaplain, of the Canartic".
    The third letter (4 pages) is possibly a transcript from an earlier correspondence, and contains the postscript "This letter was written by Capt. [Trevenner?] to his wife in June 1790 just before the battle between the Swiss and Russians in which action he was killed.-an English officer in the Russian service"
    Note about Capt. Trevennor in previous letter, possibly added later.
    This letter is followed by 8 pages of transcriptions from biblical and religious texts.
    After this is bound a one leaf (2 pages) transcription of a letter which begins with: "Your profession in its Exercise throws great light upon a beautiful part of the 107th Psalm, the whole of which..." at end: "Extract of a letter to the dear friend whose loss I must ever deplore, but who, I trust is now in the full enjoyment of the blessings above described and which..."
    Last 10 pages contain 8 pages of transcriptions from texts mostly of a religious nature followed by a letter with header "Clifton June 15th 1802", addressed to Lieut. Farington and signed "your most true and sincere friend, M.C." that begins: "The extracts I have made are so [?] my dear friend & have afforded me so much & w[ell?] comfort in moments of the keenest anguish..."
  - Manuscript containing notes and transcriptions from religious writings given by M. Church to William Farington, 1802 July (Box 1, Folder 32)
    First 4 pages are composed of 2 small leaves containing verses in ink; in pencil at top: "This was written by a Lady a few days before her death & addressed to her husband."